<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An invitation to the aforementioned society, or little common-wealth shewing the excellency of the true Christian love and the folly of all those who consider not to what end the Lord of heaven and earth hath created them.</title>
            <author>Plockhoy, Pieter Corneliszoon, fl. 1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10745875</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10745875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45958)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1405:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An invitation to the aforementioned society, or little common-wealth shewing the excellency of the true Christian love and the folly of all those who consider not to what end the Lord of heaven and earth hath created them.</title>
                  <author>Plockhoy, Pieter Corneliszoon, fl. 1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 2 of A way propounded to make the poor in these and other nations happy.</note>
                  <note>Occasionally attributed to Hugh Peters.</note>
                  <note>"Remainder sheets of the 1659 edition; in this copy imprint date has been corrected in ink to 1660."--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cooperation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45629:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45629:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN INVITATION TO THE Aforementioned SOCIETY OR LITTLE COMMON-WEALTH.</p>
            <p>SHEWING The excellency of the true Chriſtian love, and the folly of all thoſe who conſider not to what end the Lord of heaven and earth hath created them.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 12. 50.</bibl>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall do the will of my Father which is in heaven, the ſame is my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Siſter, and Mother.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpread Eagle neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45629:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45629:2"/>
            <head>An invitation to the aforementioned Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or little Common-wealth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough men are bound one to another upon ſeveral accounts, &amp; knit together with very ſtreight bonds, and that the likeneſs either of manners, or of life &amp; converſation, or of parentage and education, begets a mutual friendſhip between them, yet this is the moſt perfect, and of all others, the moſt bleſſed, when God by the diſpenſation of his ſecret counſel joyned ſome ſuch together as do agree with his divine will, &amp; with the rules of nature, &amp; they will not exchange their union or fellowſhip for all the riches in the World.</p>
            <p>But the more divine this ſtate of friendſhip is, the ſeldomer is it ſeen amongſt us, and the more is Satan (that enemy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind) againſt it, who knows full well that he hath not ſo much right or power to meddle with this holy fire, and the matter which maintaineth it, as he hath where either recreation or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage is onely looked after; which kind of friendſhips he uſeth with very little trouble to diſſolve; but in this way of amity, God onely is the bond wherewith they are tyed together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being liable to be unlooſed, and upon which foundation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fix'd, they reſolve to withſtand all aſſaults whatſoever.</p>
            <p>If then there be any felicity in the life of man, or any effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious remedy to prevent his future miſery; I conceive nothing was ever more ſolacing or reviving, and come nearer to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature, then love, <hi>viz.</hi> true love, which doth ſo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it ſelf in, and to that wherewith it reciprocates, that it ſeems to have exchanged therewith, and made over thereto, whatſoever it did poſſeſs before; ſo that amongſt true friends there is ſuch an agreement, that no ſecret, no joy, no profit, nor any croſs or affliction is undivided, but whatſoever betides either of them, is no otherwiſe then if it were the change of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſo that death it ſelf can ſcarce ſeperate ſouls ſo totally united; certainly the Heathens (who in all things purſued that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45629:3"/>
which they eſteemed beſt, found nothing more delightſom then perfect friendſhip.</p>
            <p>But how far doth Chriſt excel all others in love, who by his Doctrine and Example hath inſtituted a partnerſhip or ſociety of mutual love by the denomination of Brethren, aboliſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Diſciples, all preheminency or domineering of one over another, requiring that the gifts and means of ſubſiſtence in the World (for neceſſity and delight) ſhould be common, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving called his people to a moderation, and to a life ſutable to pure nature, ſo that all Chriſtendom ought to be meerly a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain great fraternity, conſiſting of ſuch as (having denied the World and their own luſts) conſpire together in Chriſt, the ſole head and ſpring of love, doing well to one another, and for his ſake diſtribute their goods to thoſe that ſtand in need.</p>
            <p>Oh that we had this perfection, and were anſwerable to the end of our creation! certainly there would not be ſuch going to law, ſuch intrenching and incroaching upon the bounds of lands, ſuch hiding and cloſe locking up of money, nor would there be ſuch ſcraping together of ſuperfluous Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Oh total ſum and higheſt pitch of all good! if any may be admitted (and that in due time) to this divine favour; for even many decrippid aged perſons do ſeldom attain to this; Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Kings, Princes, &amp;c. having ſpent all their years, all their ſtrength of body and ſoul, have little or no time left them to ſerve a better Maſter then the World; and therefore if God do join ſome ſuch together as endeavour after a life more regular then their former, each of them being at a loſs for a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to better and promote his reſolution, one to whom he may communicate his ſecrets, a friendly reprover of his errors, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimer of him from the Worlds allurements, a comforter in adverſity, a moderator of joy in proſperity, and in all reſpects a ſharer in that which God hath liberally given; and laſt of all, one ready for all caſes and conditions that may happen: I ſay and judge, that theſe are the happieſt of all perſons that ever were upon the earth. For as no painfuller or miſerabler thing can be thought on then that life which a man lives according to the courſe of the world; ſo nothing is more acceptable and lovely in the Univerſe, then that harmony and concord which hath its Original from God, and influence upon the man that is joyned with his fellow-man, ſo agreeable to his mind; which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45629:3"/>
certainly can be found no where, but there onely, where a firm love, agreement, and concurring will in well doing, as alſo a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral diſtribution and imparting of all created things is enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>It is evident that the moſt wiſe God would honor the ſacred ſociety of Matrimony, with the utmoſt perfection of this ſo great love, ſince they that are ſo joyned together, and built upon the right foundation, have not onely their goods, but alſo their joys and griefs common, and cannot be ſevered by any kind of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, or malicious endeavours of the envious.</p>
            <p>The World hath her delight in different degrees of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſtates, titles, and offices, exalting themſelves one above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but Chriſt on the contrary will that every one ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his office as a member of one and the ſame body, in which no one exalteth it ſelf, nor accounteth it ſelf worthier then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the eye is not puffed up becauſe it ſees; the foot is not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that it ſees not; if any member in the body is blemiſhed, it is carefully covered by the other; if any be weak, it is diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided for by the reſt; whereas on the contrary, every one in the World (which by his Office or Title is differenced from others) conceives he is quite another thing, and in himſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then others, and muſt be reputed for one that is ſet together and compoſed of ſome finer ſubſtance, and deſigned to a ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er life, yea, to an higher place in heaven then others.</p>
            <p>Now if you do but diveſt and ſtrip the World of her Riches, Honors and State, how naked and rufully forlorn will ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main? and how far different wil ſhe be found from that ſhe ſeems to be? and then it will be eaſie to believe that ſhe is ſhored up by nothing elſe but wormeaten props, which if they were once pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away, they would be fitted and made free for the imitation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Do but ſee (oh man!) what kind of things they are which do ſhut the door againſt true love, and hinder communion or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Nugatory, frivolous things, and trifles, which onely conſiſteth in a vain eſteem and opinion which ſome of the very heathens who ſaw a little further then others, did laugh at.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, Riches and Eſtates, which as our natures are ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are altogether ſuperfluous, and very troubleſome, the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whereof, who doth not ſee it? They are a burthen to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45629:4"/>
to the rich, cauſing them to fill their houſes with variety of coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furniture, which in many years (or never) happens not to be uſeful to them; they are a trouble to get them; a perplexity to keep them, and a grief to part with them; their houſes are ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and great, ſo that there is either much void and empty room within, or elſe they put themſelves to a great deal of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and moleſtation in furniſhing and filling them; their clothes are ſo dainty and curious that they cannot ſit down any where without fear of ſpoiling their Apparel; and unleſs they have ſome to behold their ſplendor, all is little to them; but if they have ſpectators, they fear ſome will lurch, and others filch away from them; their ſleep is almoſt none. Oh how great a miſery is it to be laden with riches!</p>
            <p>Secondly, Honor and Dignities, which if we meaſure accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the deſign of nature, and the rule of Chriſt, may not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be diſtinguiſhed then by ſeveral Names or denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of divers members of one and the ſame body; the name of the tongue; is that any more worthy name then the name of the finger? The name of the eye; is that more excellent then the name of the breaſt? No certainly; that whereby the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are differenced, doth not lift them up; as with us the name of Lord and Gentleman puffeth up; and what elſe is it but a meer Name, the vanity whereof who ſees it not? The very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of it is nothing elſe but the noiſe of the tongue, and the report of others; or the knee, or the hat, all fleeting and varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things that are to be bought for a very ſmall matter; and yet we are oftentimes ſo fooliſh, that though ſuch things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly come not from the heart, neither are fruits of an upright and ſincere mind; nay, when on the contrary our own minds do ſuggeſt to us, that there is I know not what kind of tacit derifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it, and doth oftentimes ſignifie nothing elſe but hatred and ill-will, yet we do delight in ſuch trifles, and give way to them ſo far, that we will rather hear a lye from a notorious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſite or flatterer, if it be but on our ſide, then to hear the truth from an honeſt man, if it croſs our intereſt.</p>
            <p>Do but now caſt up thy account (oh man!) how dearly thou haſt ventured to buy the friendſhip of the World, which yet thou never foundſt to be thy friend, but feignedly, and that for a ſpurt; on the contrary, conſider how little, or almoſt nothing, thou haſt beſt owed to anſwer the love of God, who nevertheleſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45629:4"/>
would have been the moſt aſſured, and moſt faithful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable friend.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt trimmed and decked thy body, and in Apparel thou haſt been paſſing ſumptuous, that ſome ſilly creature might gaze on thee with admiration: In feaſts thou haſt been prodigal, that thy companions and aſſociates might commend thee; thou haſt diſtributed thy gifts and preſents, that thou mayeſt ſeem liberal; thou haſt put forth thy art and skill, that thou maiſt be called and accounted learned; thou haſt daubed thy houſe with many colours, to cauſe them to ſtand ſtill that paſs by; in the mean time thy reward hath been nothing elſe but a great toyl, and the ſudden, uncompoſed, diſagreeing, and unreaſonable judgement and cenſure of other men: Conſider in the mean while whether thou haſt provoked God thereby, or honoured him; it is moſt certain that thou mighteſt have ſerved God, and have performed the office of love to thy neighbor at a far chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per rate; for by how much profuſe and ſlaviſh thou haſt been in the ſervice of the World, by ſo much the more haſt thou been partimonious and ſparing in the ſervice of God; for it is evident the World requires coſtly attendance, as to all her matters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſollicitous of the heart, how it ſtands with that, if you be but careful that nothing be wanting in outward appearance, in diſſembling and complemental deportments; or if there be but ceremony and external ſemblance, and fine ſhew enough, ſo that by the very aſpect it is plain that the ſlaves of the World may be diſcerned from the true ſervants of God, in as much as the firſt are moveable, flexible, fickle, and variable; but the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have their eyes alwayes fixed upon the mark which is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
            <p>If we but once bring our ſelves to the touch and travel through the World, with a free and pure mind, we ſhall be able to obtain ſo much from our ſelves as in Chriſtian ſimplicity, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and unincumbredneſs, to exclude the Wiſdom, Eloquence and Prudence of the World, concluding (as in truth it is) that nothing is to be compared with our Maſter Chriſt, and that none other knows any thing, or can give any counſel that is ſavingly profitable, but he; nor ſhall we repute them happy who have no other character or ſuperſcription then the Worlds Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, knowing that Worldly knowledge is not ſo great a thing as it is commonly eſteemed, for as much as under the title and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45629:5"/>
diſguiſe of learned, the very ſhame of being found ignorant, doth (with many inventions and cheating ſubterfuges) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the hiding of it ſelf from being diſcovered to the eyes of the common people.</p>
            <p>Shall we never be able to attain to that equal judgement in putting a true value upon real vertue whereſoever it be found, as well in a beggar as in a Prince? and to leave off more to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Ornaments of a Magiſtrate, then the Office he ſuſtains? and eſteeming leſs of poverty, then of ſuperfluity? of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, then of the ſtate? of a good conſcience, leſs then of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular or vain applauſe? of a piece of bread, then of delicious dainties? of Water, then Wine? of a green bank of Turf? then of a coſtly Couch?</p>
            <p>Shall we not be able to arrive to this, to eſteem one onely Sentence of the holy Scriptures more then the higheſt accute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all the Worlds Philoſophy? We ſhall be able to do it if we did well weigh that the Worlds turn is but a ſhort Comedy, and that we are but Actors who appear no more then once upon the Stage; and if we did ſeriouſly conſider that all things are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and repreſented to us in the World far otherwiſe then they are in themſelves, but eſpecially when we have well pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that honeſt and godly people after a very little while are to expect a participation and enjoyment of another kind of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and dignity then any the World promiſeth.</p>
            <p>Shall we never be able to attain to this, to chuſe rather to lay up our Eſtates in the hungry bellies of the poor, then in a few bags? to lay the foundation of our praiſe upon the prayers of the poor? to make the croſs of Chriſt our glory, and not to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew the diſſavour of man, as the reward of our well-doing? In a word, to put off all deſire of fame and renown, as alſo to refer all deſire of revenge, to the judgement of Chriſt; we ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do all this, if we forget not that our God is the moſt faithful of all Debtors, and the moſt ſure of all Securities; if al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we never forget that his praiſe which ſhall be given to us in the preſence of men and Angels, is the moſt glorious praiſe, and that his renumerations and recompences are the moſt noble and everlaſting.</p>
            <p>To how happy an hour are we born if we do enter upon this communion or fellowſhip! And from how many vexations will it releaſe us! Whereof the Heathens, having obtained but a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45629:5"/>
ſhadow, how magnanimouſly did they in their mindes ſoar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft above all Kings, and worldly glory? how did they deſpiſe all terrene affairs (as they that from above look down upon that which is below) and had pitty on them, and ſo did indeed avoid the greateſt miſeries of mans life.</p>
            <p>But ſince Chriſtian Religion is come into the world, it is a wonderful thing to conſider what a light brake in together with it, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch a light that all they whoſe hearts were touched therewith, throwing all from them, betook themſelves to it for refuge, as to a true and ſtedfaſt liberty after a long and horrible captivity, eaſily forgetting their riches, ſtate, rule and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, forſaking Parents, Wife, Children, Relations, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever before was moſt neer and dear unto them, not being by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations of Tyrants, to be drawn from the ſweetneſs of the Chriſtian life.</p>
            <p>The ſame have appeared in the memory of our Fore-fathers, when the bonds of Antichriſt (it is ſtrange to think how firm they were) were broken, when they vvho a little before were forced to creep upon the ground began to riſe up, with what readineſs that syrannical Worſhip of Invocating ſo many deceaſed Saints was rejected, and the unconfined Worſhip of God re-entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And with what readineſs that vain (though gainfull) fancy of Invocating Chriſt by ſo many Interceſſions came to nought; ſo that it appears in all reſpects, how much God hath chalked out in nature it ſelf the pure and true Worſhip, as alſo the ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and friendly converſation of man, and likewiſe how eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe things which are contrary thereto, periſh and come to nothing, and how far our Religion with-draweth us from all Theatrical or Stage-play geſtures, and countenances, and all thoſe troubleſom Ceremonies wherewith we torture our ſelves, in ſpeaking, eating, ſaluting, walking, cloathing, yea and in all the actions of our life: But on the contrary, how conformable it maketh us to the coeleſtial Hierarchie and natural Policie, and yet in theſe petty and altogether childiſh things, men are ſo hard to be convinced and drawn off from them, as if all their well-being depended thereon, and the beatitude or happineſs of all mankind had all its foundation therein, and never give ſo much ſcope to reaſon and well-guided underſtanding, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to acknowledge their vanity, or if it be known to them, rather to throw it off then to retain and daily augment it with new and exottick bawbles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45629:6"/>
In truth, as often as we do ſtrictly ponder to what end God the Creator and Ruler of all things, hath brought every one of us into this great Fabrick of the World, and yet for us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that the life of almoſt all men is either unprofitable, idle, wicked, or hurtful to mankind; we have reaſon to be afraid and jealous of our ſelves, leaſt peradventure either by the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the times, or our education, we have applyed our ſelves to ſome manner of life which is not ſutable to the will of God, and the end of our Creation, being not able to give a juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count wherein we have lived to the glory of God, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of mankind.</p>
            <p>Certainly to have eaten, to have drunk, to have ſlept, yea to have read much, writ much, ſeen, heard, and travelled much, and let this alſo be added, to have managed an Eſtate, to have kept Hounds, Horſes and Servants; to have had Arts and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in great eſteem; to have trimmed up Houſes, to have often made Banquets; to have born Titles of Honor; to have collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many Books together; in a word, to have been imployed and very buſie to the uttermoſt, in things that do not relate or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Chriſt, let them be what they will, certainly all that will never ſatisfie God, nor endure the touch or tryal of the fire but being conſumed as ſtubble, will leave man bare and naked, a Malefactor, and guilty in the preſence of God for his loſt time, and his neglect of friendſhip and union with God, together with the neglect of the Endowments, as wel of body, as of ſpirit, ſo that there will be an horrible diſtance between them and thoſe whoſe faith in God, and love to man, hath been ſteadfaſt and firm.</p>
            <p>Let us take heed Brethren, leaſt thoſe among us who either in underſtanding, learning, riches, beauty, or arts, excel others, do conceit that God is therefore more gracious and favourable to them then others, and that they have attained to the beſt life; for ſuch men do groſly deceive themſelves, becauſe the manner of Gods judging is quite different from that of the World, his eyes are quite other kind of eyes, and his pollicy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the Worlds pollicy, as much as Heaven from Earth, as one vvho chuſeth the unvvorthy and deſpiſed, rejecteth and abhorreth that vvhich the World do highly eſteem.</p>
            <p>If any think this our Society and Fellovvſhip to be a nevv thing, ſo that he cannot (as it vvas in old time) ſo much as point
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45629:6"/>
out five pair of ſuch friends, he hath reaſon with me to lament, that while men do curiouſly, and with anxity of mind, ſearch into the courſe of the Stars &amp; Planets, the vertues of Plants &amp; Vigitables, yea into the very bowels of the earth, yet they are ſo neglective of their ſalvation, that they do not (in the leaſt) ſo much as ſeek and look after that life for which they would not need ſo much Silver and Gold, ſo many Titles of Honor, ſo many Buildings, ſuch Clothes, ſo much Furniture for their Houſes, ſo many Meſſes and Diſhes at their Meals, ſo many Arms and Ammunition, or Warlike proviſions, ſo many Judgements or Decrees of Law, ſo many Medicines, nor ſo many Books, all which are cauſes of vaſt trouble, ſo that the men of the World themſelves (if they were but wiſe) would avoid theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, or (as they themſelves do confeſs) neceſſities of ſinning.</p>
            <p>This Society or fellowſhip hath not always been ſo rare, and ſo thin ſown, but was very rife in the primitive times, till the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the firſt innocency did inſinuate themſelves thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, whereby the life which men were bound to live, as in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Laws of Chriſt, began to be accounted ſuch as a man may chuſe whether he would imbrace or no, and take up a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious and ſuperoragatory life, comprizing ſuch a ſanctimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or holineſs as was more then neceſſary to ſalvation, and was onely to be uſed by ſuch as deſired a greater reward in Heaven then others; which opinion gave a beginning to many Orders of lazie and wanton beaſts, (I mean Monks, and the like) and of many thouſand fables &amp; cheats, which things when men came to themſelves, they did juſtly reject; and when they are grown wiſer, they wil totally caſt off, even thoſe poor ones who now ſcrape and rake together the riches of the World, as alſo thoſe (ſeeming) humble and lowly perſons that now take up the high Seats of the World, and ſuch pretended ſimple ones who now fill and diſturb the whole World with their cunning and deceit.</p>
            <p>But for us, let us hold faſt that which is in this life the beſt thing, <hi>viz.</hi> The univerſal love to Gods creation; and if we be inſufferable to the World, and they be incorrigible or unbette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as to us, then let us reduce our friendſhip and ſociety to a few in number, and maintain it in ſuch places as are ſeperate from other men, where we may with leſs impediment or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, love one another, and mind the Wonders of God, eating the bread we ſhall earn with our own hands, leaving nothing to the body but what its nakedneſs, hunger, thirſt, and wearineſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45629:7"/>
calls for, to help our neceſſity and health, then it will appear how many things we may well be without, what things we may refrain, and what kind of matters we ought not to know; how many things we may avoid, in what things we may beſt quiet our ſelves, and how far eaſier we may ſatisfie Chriſt in his little ones with a penny, then the World with a pound.</p>
            <p>For Princes are not born on purpoſe to rear up ſtately Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rned are not born for the writing of many unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and (for the moſt part) frivolous Books; the rich are not born to boaſt of their gold, ſilver and chriſtal-Veſſels; the reſt of the people are not born for ſo many various unprofitable Handy-crafts: In a word, mankind is not born for ſo many kinds of education, of being rich, and running into exceſs; but all theſe racks of the mind it hath invented of it ſelf, and now made a cuſtom and habitual, ſo that it hath made the life more grievous to it ſelf every day, under ſo many painful and labourſome inventions.</p>
            <p>Now I would that they that ſtand and admire at the fine Wits of our age, and the ſublime learning of our times, did but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with me, Whether theſe things which daily pleaſe our eyes with their novelty, be indeed ſuch for which we may juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice; or whether on the contrary it were not much better (ſince they are the cauſe of ſo many griefs and troubles in mans life) that we were wiſhed and adviſed by our learned men to put them away far from us.</p>
            <p>For what greater fruit of Wiſdom, or what greater glory of the new revived learning could there poſſibly be, then by that to bring humane matters to ſuch a poſture that we may attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute our well-being and felicity in this life to them under God, that by the wholeſom inſtruction thereof, that which is ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, uſeleſs and unnecſſary, might be thrown away, and that which is nugatory, trifling and unprofitable, might be cut off, and that we might truly be diſtinguiſhed from the barbarous &amp; ſavage people, not by Books, nor by Titles of Honor, nor by U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, but by ſuch morality as Chriſtian Philoſophy doth preſcribe.</p>
            <p>Let there come forth from the Studies and Liberaries of our Wiſe men into the light, not a continuation or proſecution of old Errors, or an heaping up of new to the old, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, a Rule or Direction for a new and reformed life in Chriſt, which may demonſtrate, that as we are profeſſors of the beſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45629:7"/>
Religion, we are alſo imitators of the beſt life; then ſhall we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their Society or Fellowſhip, and be ſubject to their good Lavvs and Orders, and obſerve their rational Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>In the mean time let them not take it ill that we do not make any great ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ount of theſe Sciences that are void of Chriſt, that we do not deſire to know them; and if we have drunk in any ſuch, yet we deſire to unlearn them, and with ſingleneſs of heart to become as children, who are altogether unacquainted with voluptuouſneſs, ceremonies, riches, and fooliſh labour; hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward we deſire to live towards God, in unincumbredneſs, void of carking for the multiplicity of ſuper-neceſſary things, exerciſing a delight in real equality, and for the reſt, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Chriſt onely for our Lord and Maſter, and in this School of his we hope that neither Divine Myſteries, nor ſecrets of Nature, nor the contemplation of rare matters, ſhall be wanting to us, ſince he formerly hath made it evident by the example of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and holy men, how powerful he is in teaching, and then eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially he diſplayeth his riches, and opens his unexhauſtible treaſures when humane Wiſdom ceaſeth, and the skill of the World melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away.</p>
            <p>But that we now are ſo weak, &amp; the ſtrength of our Religion that is grown ſo faint with us, that the Majeſty of the Divine preſence, with the miraculous working, is removed from us, whom ſhall we accuſe for this, but our ſelves, who in the midſt of the Divine Light have ſcarce retained any more then the bare name, being content if we may but be called Chriſtians, as to the reſt being altogether like to the World? So that it is no marvel that we who do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel others in the purſuit of honeſt actions, as Juſtice, Mercy, and the propagation of the Name of Chriſt, nor in the education of children, do not alſo in the leaſt go beyond them in thoſe gifts which were peculiar to upright and zealous Chriſtians; and yet we ought in ſo clear a light of the Goſpel as we have, to be ſo far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed as to excel other men; ſo that if others do not commit Adultery, we ſhould not ſo much as deſire another mans Wife; if they do not commit Murther, we ſhould not at all be angry with our brother; if they love them that are like to them, we ſhould love our enemies; if they do lend to thoſe that have to give again, we ſhould lend to thoſe from whom we cannot hope to receive any thing again; for it becometh us who hope for the inheritance of an eternal life, in all things to go beyond thoſe that know one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45629:8"/>
this preſent life: But if (nevertheleſs) we be found beneath theſe, or if we be found but like to them, and no more, how much will their accuſation preſs us down, and condemn us to the like, yea to a more grievous puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Let us look back to the former Ages, and it will appear that the Divine Power was then moſt of all vigorous and eminent, when there was not ſuch oſtentation of fine Wits, but the ſupream know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was then placed in the Croſs of Chriſt; but now while mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters go quite otherwiſe, and the creatures of our brain do obum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, or overſhadow and obſcure the Works of God, we do things according to the will and pleaſure of Satan, who being the moſt ſubtile of all Philoſophers, Logicians, and Artiſts, is not afraid of us if we go his way; and by that occaſion he inſinuateth himſelf more and more into us, and glideth in by means of ſuch things which we moſt admire.</p>
            <p>Do not you ſee, Brethren, that by the goodneſs and long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, it is in our hand and power, now we have taſted of the bitterneſs of this Worlds pleaſure, to rid our ſelves of very many troubles, going on by a way that is not crooked and rugged, but ſtraight and ſmooth, tending to the true reſt, and higheſt pitch of all perfection, by applying our ſelves to this Communion or Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whereof we have made mention, which ſuffereth no pride, riot, exceſs, uncleanneſs, injuſtice, or any evils which have been pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed in their native colours; from which Society no man that profeſſeth the Name of Chriſt, and practiſeth his Doctrine, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, of what ſect, party, or by what Name ſoever he is called or known.</p>
            <p>We deſire therefore, that all who love their own peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, will conſider of our Order or Inſtitution, which is propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a general rule; for we judge it to be not onely a true oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all evil, but alſo a means to rid the World of all unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and hurtful Handy-crafts, being the cauſe of ſin and ſlavery; to which we hope that God (who is the Husband of Widows, and a Father of the fatherleſs) will vouchſafe his bleſſing, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that ſo the pure and uncorrupted Worſhip (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts more in well-doing, then in much ſpeaking) may break forth to the glory of his holy Name, and the good of all mankind.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45629:8"/>
            <head>A Letter written in order to the now mentioned Society, or little Common-Wealth, by ſome well-affected perſons, whoſe hearts and hands have already joyned therein, to ſtir up all ſuch who are truly ſenſible of the poor and needy, to carry on this ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and charitable a work.</head>
            <p>HAving not onely conſidered the poverty, afflictions, and ſtreights of many well-minded people, together with the evil conſequences that ariſe from the corrupt cuſtoms and wayes of moſt employments, and the general diſorder proceeding from riches and poverty; but alſo the way propounded by the endeavours of our friend <hi>Peter Corneliſſon,</hi> to rectifie all ſuch and many other inconveniences, by bringing together a fit, ſutable, and well qualified people, into one Houſhold-government, or little Common-wealth, wherein every one may keep his propriety, and be imployed in ſome work or other, as he ſhall be fit, without being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as is more at large expreſſed in a Platform to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Whereupon we are reſolved judging it to be neceſſary, and our duty to promote ſo good and pious a work, with the aſſiſtance of other mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and rational men, to lay ſuch a foundation as may tend to the relief of the oppreſſed, the preſerving of ſuch as are in danger of falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptations and ſnares, and the increaſe of underſtanding and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al love, as alſo the exemplary ordering of ſuch acts as may be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by prudential charity.</p>
            <p>And hereunto we do earneſtly invite all perſons that have a willing mind to do good according to their abilities, ſome by their wiſdom and counſel, others by money and credit, or by both, as they ſhall be able and free, that ſo a ſtock may be raiſed for the carrying on of this good and beneficial work.</p>
            <p>To which end we have ſubſcribed our Names, and the ſums of money which we are willing to give, hoping that all ſuch as are for ſo general a work, will upon due conſideration likewiſe ſubſcribe for ſuch a ſum of money as they are willing to give towards the accompliſhment of the premiſes, and meet together to confer and order the ſaid ſums of moneys into the hands of ſome truſty perſons, for the uſe and benefit of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45629:9"/>
onely, and what elſe ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound conducing to the perfecting of this work, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll the Society can ſubſiſt of it ſelf in order, which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on be, from the credible information of divers perſons, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that many hundreds in <hi>Tranſilvania, Hungaria,</hi> and the <hi>Palts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graves</hi> Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, from a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll beginning have attained not onely to a very comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>table life among themſelves, but alſo ability of doing much good to others not of their Societies.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Subſcribed towards the raiſing of a Stock, as follovvs.</head>
                  <item>I. S. — 100. l.</item>
                  <item>VV. R. — 100. l.</item>
                  <item>C. O. — 10. l.</item>
                  <item>VV. VV. — 20. l.</item>
                  <item>R. S. — 10. l.</item>
                  <item>P. C. — 20. l.</item>
                  <item>H. D — 50. l.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45629:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
